Phonetic transcription equals mathematical notation. If you accept that 2 times 2 can
also be written 2 squared, you're comfortable with multiple labels for a
single concept. This is the same principle as the word cat, also being written as k
digraph a t, cat. Here's a simple two-part rule for the letter O. One. In a one
-syllable word, O sounds like ah, unless the word ends in E. hot, lost, tom, bob,
dot com. Two, in a stress syllable, O also sounds like ah. Possible, Holland,
philosophy. Here's a two-part rule for the letter A. One, in a one-syllable word, A
sounds like ah, unless the word ends in E. Cat, Sam, drab. Two, in a stress syllable,
A sounds like ah. functional, manager, catastrophe. Once you've internalized the
basic rules of phonetics, you need to diligently, persistently, and stubbornly
apply them universally. In computing terms, think of doing a global search all
and replace. Some people have an initial aversion to reading phonetics because it's
new and confusing. It doesn't even look like English. This is where we're going to
have you practice some of that open-mindedness and trust, except that if you
read the phonetics, you will have an American accent. An accountant kept making
the same pronunciation errors in English over and over again, asked why, her
response was consistently, I forgot. When asked if she forgot arithmetic, the answer
was, well, of course not, that would make my life miserable. Well, not applying the
phonetics was making her life miserable.